<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Jose M. Perez&#39;s Blog</title>
  <subtitle>Web development, performance, and some other good practices.</subtitle>
  <link href="/tag/web/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="https://jmperezperez.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-12-16T17:51:46.000Z</updated>
  <id>https://jmperezperez.com/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Jose M. Perez</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The (mobile) web is making a come-back</title>
    <link href="https://jmperezperez.com//web-is-back"/>
    <id>https://jmperezperez.com//web-is-back</id>
    <published>2017-06-29T11:10:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-12-16T17:51:46.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The web ecosystem is maturing and every day we understand better how to architecture large and maintainable web applications. We also understand what makes our sites slower and are coming up with solutions to overcome this.</p>
<p>Building a complex site that can work on slow networks is a challenge. One that some companies have decided to accept without fear and share with the developer community.</p>
<span id="more"></span>

<h2 id="Western-companies-looking-at-users-from-developing-countries"><a href="#Western-companies-looking-at-users-from-developing-countries" class="headerlink" title="Western companies looking at users from developing countries"></a>Western companies looking at users from developing countries</h2><p>Instagram, Twitter, Uber, Tinder. They have in common that they are well known in the developed world, and also that they have embraced the web as the channel to reach users in emerging markets. Not as a basic site with a large modal to download the app, but with a full-feature experience. After all, web users shouldn’t be considered second-class citizens.</p>
<p>Twitter has been great at talking about implementation details (see <a href="https://blog.twitter.com/official/en_us/topics/product/2017/introducing-twitter-lite.html">Introducing Twitter Lite</a> and <a href="https://medium.com/@paularmstrong/twitter-lite-and-high-performance-react-progressive-web-apps-at-scale-d28a00e780a3">Twitter Lite and High Performance React Progressive Web Apps at Scale</a>) which is really helpful for devs like me who face some of these challenges on a daily basis. And, because anyone can see the code you ship, it’s easy to look <a href="https://medium.com/statuscode/dissecting-twitters-redux-store-d7280b62c6b1">into the details</a>.</p>
<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/twitter-lite.png" alt="Twitter Lite&#39;s saving options"></p>
<p><small class="caption">Twitter Lite also offers an option to save data.</small></p>
<p>The case of Instagram is notable too because of its scale. They recently <a href="http://fortune.com/2017/05/09/instagram-mobile-website-upload-photos/">added photo upload</a> to their mobile site in a clear sign of their investment on the platform, but haven’t shared details about how the tech behind the site. Tinder is a similar case, with <a href="http://blog.gotinder.com/introducing-tinder-online/">a newer website</a>.</p>
<p>And a couple of days ago it was Uber with <a href="https://eng.uber.com/m-uber/">Building m.uber: Engineering a high-performance web app for the global market</a>. They describe their JS stack, some interesting things they are doing to reduce the payload and also what they plan for the future.</p>
<p><a href="https://building.calibreapp.com/beyond-the-bubble-real-world-performance-9c991dcd5342">It’s evident where the next Internet users are going to come from</a> and no big company wants to miss the opportunity.</p>
<h2 id="Emerging-markets-leading-PWA"><a href="#Emerging-markets-leading-PWA" class="headerlink" title="Emerging markets leading PWA"></a>Emerging markets leading PWA</h2><p>If you want to find the leading companies on web development stop looking in Silicon Valley and turn your head towards India and China. There is no talk from Google about PWA where a company from from these countries doesn’t showcase their site. <a href="http://flipkart.com/">Flipkart</a>, <a href="https://www.treebo.com/">Treebo</a>, <a href="https://housing.com/">Housing</a>, and <a href="https://www.ele.me/">ele.me</a> are some examples. Have a look at the recent <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aCMbSyngXB4">Production Progressive Web Apps With JavaScript Frameworks (Google I/O ‘17)</a>.</p>
<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/flipkart-pwa.png" alt="Flipkart&#39;s PWA seems to be improving important metrics"></p>
<p><small class="caption">Some insights from Flipkart and the impact of their mobile site.</small></p>
<p>Before anyone else they saw the benefits of building sites that can work offline and can work fine on a slow network without the hassle of app downloads and updates.</p>
<p>I believe this is good for users, but also for companies. Updating web content is almost instantaneous. This means deploying new features, but also fixing bugs. And believe me, when there is a big issue and you need to fix something right now, time is precious.</p>
<p>Developers can ship code without an expensive process of building whole apps and have them go through a submission/revision system. They also benefit from quicker feedback loops when coding and seeing their changes on the screen (to be fair, React Native is making this one way better in the native world).</p>
<h2 id="The-mobile-web-in-2017"><a href="#The-mobile-web-in-2017" class="headerlink" title="The mobile web in 2017"></a>The mobile web in 2017</h2><p>When I saw <a href="https://twitter.com/markdalgleish/status/879144162389393409">this tweet</a> I laughed out loud.</p>
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en-gb"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Updated: The mobile web in 2017, **now with web fonts!**<br><br>(Original: <a href="https://t.co/nLta2tqk42">https://t.co/nLta2tqk42</a>) <a href="https://t.co/c4ZgEdkbU8">pic.twitter.com/c4ZgEdkbU8</a></p>&mdash; Mark Dalgleish (@markdalgleish) <a href="https://twitter.com/markdalgleish/status/879144162389393409">26 June 2017</a></blockquote>
<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

<p>A moment later I got sad since this is quite true. It seems that everyone at every company assumes that apps are more engaging and retain users better than a web experience.</p>
<p>This is true when:</p>
<ul>
<li>a) you haven’t made an effort in making your web better,</li>
<li>b) you don’t hesitate in adding 3rd party tracking code that worsens your site</li>
<li>c) you fill the screen with banners and modals, hiding the actual content.</li>
</ul>
<p>Have a look at <a href="https://twitter.com/sbholtrop/status/878611398527520768">this tweet and its thread</a>. You’ll see screenshots that should probably remind some of your past experiences browsing the web on mobile.</p>
<h2 id="What-does-the-future-look-like"><a href="#What-does-the-future-look-like" class="headerlink" title="What does the future look like?"></a>What does the future look like?</h2><p>I don’t know if the importance of the mobile apps will decrease, or whether those mobile web users will eventually use apps instead of the web. Will even network speed be a problem in the future?</p>
<p>It’s very interesting to see these trends going back and forth. At a minimum, we should always build for our users and avoid assumptions. Not all of them use powerful MacBook Pros nor have the latest iPhone.</p>
<p>We are paid to face these challenges, to serve our users. Let’s prioritise that instead of developer ergonomics and everyone will benefit.</p>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Some recent examples of large companies implementing Progressive Web Apps, changing their mobile strategy
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="web" scheme="https://jmperezperez.com/tags/web/"/>
    
      <category term="pwa" scheme="https://jmperezperez.com/tags/pwa/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Reading List</title>
    <link href="https://jmperezperez.com//2017-07-reading-list"/>
    <id>https://jmperezperez.com//2017-07-reading-list</id>
    <published>2017-06-29T11:10:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-12-22T08:33:15.000Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a list of some posts and talks I have read and watch during the last days. I write it to keep track of interesting content for myself, but you might also find it useful.</p>
<span id="more"></span>

<h2 id="Posts"><a href="#Posts" class="headerlink" title="Posts"></a>Posts</h2><ul>
<li><p><a href="https://twitter.com/jonsneyers">Jon Sneyers</a> from Cloudinary posted <a href="http://cloudinary.com/blog/detecting_the_psychovisual_impact_of_compression_related_artifacts_using_ssimulacra">Detecting the psychovisual impact of compression related artifacts using SSIMULACRA</a>. It talks about SSIM (which <a href="/ssim-jpeg-io/">I have covered in the past</a>), used to compress images based as much as possible without affecting the visual appearance (no visible artifacts). Jon describes <a href="https://github.com/cloudinary/ssimulacra">Cloudinary’s SSIMULACRA</a> and benchmarks it agains the top perceptual metrics.</p>
</li>
<li><p><a href="https://hackernoon.com/tech-companies-these-are-the-perks-and-benefits-i-want-5e9788c30958">Tech companies: these are the perks (and benefits) I want</a>. I agree with Tara’s points about what I find important in my job and hope more companies embrace them.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Tools"><a href="#Tools" class="headerlink" title="Tools"></a>Tools</h2><ul>
<li><a href="http://cloudinary.com/blog/introducing_website_speed_test_an_image_analysis_tool_integrated_with_webpagetest">Cloudinary released</a> their <a href="https://webspeedtest.cloudinary.com/">Website Speed Test Image Analysis Tool</a>, which is also integrated with WebPagetest.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/website-speed-test.png" alt="Website Speed Test"></p>
<p><small class="caption">A screenshot of Cloudinary’s Website Speed Test checking this site.</small></p>
<h2 id="Talks"><a href="#Talks" class="headerlink" title="Talks"></a>Talks</h2><ul>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/nicj">Nic Jansma</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/shubhie">Shubhie Panicker</a> gave a talk at Fluent Conf named “Reliably Measuring Responsiveness in the Wild”. <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/15DsvKVrt9vIL5s-wH4VhCGEhS-FkjD5pP3dH1-hzPi8/edit">The slides for the talk</a> are already available. They are full with great insights and are a must if you are into web performance. They show how to on measure responsiveness using old and new Browser APIs like <a href="/paint-timing-api/">PerformanceObserver</a>, and show examples from real sites and how these metrics affect conversion rates.</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/reliably-measuring-responsiveness.png" alt="Reliably measuring responsiveness"></p>
<p><small class="caption">One of the slides <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/15DsvKVrt9vIL5s-wH4VhCGEhS-FkjD5pP3dH1-hzPi8/edit">of the talk</a> explaining how to detect long tasks on our sites.</small></p>
<h2 id="Conferences"><a href="#Conferences" class="headerlink" title="Conferences"></a>Conferences</h2><ul>
<li><p><a href="https://twitter.com/pinchito">Alex Fernández</a> has published <a href="http://pinchito.es/2017/jsdayes-2017-cost.html">How Much Did JSDayES 2017 Cost?</a>. This is a conference <a href="/jsdayes-madrid-2017/">I attended</a> and it’s eye-opening to see how much effort is put behind the scenes.</p>
</li>
<li><p>I’m from Alicante, Spain, and I was very happy to find out about <a href="http://reactalicante.es/">React Alicante 2017</a>. There are not many tech conferences in the area, and I hope it is a success. I’m glad I’ll attend!</p>
</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      Reading List with some articles from June 2017
    
    </summary>
    
    
      <category term="web" scheme="https://jmperezperez.com/tags/web/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
